<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Declaration of the marks and fruits, of the false prophets: with, the discovery of the two mothers, and their teachers: from them who in the world in scorn is called Quakers, which suffers for the righteous seed sake.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D711</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E853_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207462</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866511</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866511</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118787</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82187)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118787)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 129:E853[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Declaration of the marks and fruits, of the false prophets: with, the discovery of the two mothers, and their teachers: from them who in the world in scorn is called Quakers, which suffers for the righteous seed sake.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb: 19 1655".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118787:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118787:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION OF The <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Fruits,</hi> of the falſe <hi>Prophets:</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">with, The Diſcovery of the two Mothers, and their Teachers: From them who in the World in ſcorn is called <hi>Quakers,</hi> which ſuffers for the Righteous Seed ſake.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeperate (ſaith the Lord) and touch not the Unclean Thing, and I will receive you. <bibl>2 Cor. 6. 17.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe word of the Lord to this Nation, People, Prieſts, and Magiſtrates, who be without the fear of the Lord God, &amp; regardeth not his Law, which ſaith thou ſhalt not reſpect perſons, who holds up <hi>Baal</hi> &amp; <hi>Baalam,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> receives the wages of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, gifts &amp; rewards, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Lord God ſent his <hi>Prophets</hi> &amp; ſent his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to cry againſt, as in all ages they did, which was in the Light, and which are in the Light, ſuch were Priſoned, &amp; ſuch are Priſoned now, as they then, with you that hold up ſuch as goes in the wayes of <hi>Balaam,</hi> to gifts and rewards, and in the way of <hi>Cain;</hi> ſuch (in all ages) were Perſecutors of the Righteous, where it was brought forth, (as it is now in this Nation of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland at this day, with the Generation of men and people, that are now in <hi>Cains</hi> way, and <hi>Balaams</hi> way, that pretends Chriſts words, and Prophets words, and Apoſtles words; that profeſſeth thoſe words, and pretends to worſhip God, which all is with the light ſeen which comes from Jeſus, which witneſs againſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and witneſs againſt the Unrighteous, and the Ungodly, &amp;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118787:2"/>
ſpoke of the <hi>Saints</hi> ſufferings, with the unrighteous Generation, &amp; hailing them forth of the Synagogues before Magiſtrates, which ye Rulers, Prieſts, and people of this Nation of <hi>England</hi> doth ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil the words of Chriſt: Oh the blood that hath been ſhed in this <hi>Nation,</hi> and the <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Humiliation Dayes,</hi> and <hi>fasting-dayes,</hi> &amp; for <hi>Reformation;</hi> and now they that come to walk in the Lawes of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Life</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which cannot reſpect the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> as it doth forbid, you do Priſon and perſecute with your <hi>Law,</hi> which is your <hi>Will;</hi> let that in all your <hi>Conſciences</hi> judge, and now ſee the <hi>Fruits</hi> of your <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> and the end of your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting,</hi> the end of your <hi>Humiliation-Dayes,</hi> the end of your <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is manifeſted, and be ſilent all <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> who hath not the poſſeſſion, and poſſeſſes not the Life of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and of the <hi>Apostles</hi> which gave forth the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> for ſuch <hi>Profeſſors</hi> as hath the words of the <hi>Prophet, Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> goes in <hi>Cains Way,</hi> and <hi>Balaams Way,</hi> receives the <hi>wages</hi> of <hi>Unrighteouſneſs</hi> for <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>rewards:</hi> Let the <hi>Teachers</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice witneſs it, and be their <hi>Iudge;</hi> and in <hi>Cains-Way, perſecuting,</hi> &amp; theſe their <hi>Fruits</hi> &amp; <hi>Marks</hi> be their <hi>Witneſs</hi> and their <hi>Seal,</hi> for how many <hi>Goales</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> by, and through them, have <hi>Priſoners</hi> in them, and often almoſt filled with <hi>Priſoners,</hi> which witneſs the <hi>Truth</hi> againſt <hi>Cains Generation</hi> and <hi>Balaams,</hi> which receives the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Unrighteouſneſs, Rewards and Gifts,</hi> let their practiſe it ſelf be a witneſs agaihſt them, and the <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelfe judge, and all who be in the <hi>Light,</hi> that forth it gave, who with it ſees their <hi>Fruits</hi> and <hi>Marks,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Manners,</hi> and the <hi>Manners</hi> of their <hi>People;</hi> without ſhame, <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Prieſt;</hi> without <hi>Naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,</hi> ſtrikers, ſtoners, and beaters, hailers out of the <hi>Synagogues,</hi> Punchers, and throwers down, yea, in their <hi>Synagogues,</hi> and that which they call their <hi>Temple,</hi> where they pretend to worſhip <hi>God;</hi> and theſe are their <hi>Fruits</hi> and <hi>Marks:</hi> Many of the dear <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> are there almoſt murdered, and yet are not aſhamed to call themſelves a Church, and the Miniſters of Chriſt, and the Goſpel: many have been ſore bruiſed, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118787:2"/>
wounded in that they call the place of their worſhip, where the Children of God hath been almoſt murdered; but theſe are the <hi>Fruits</hi> and <hi>Marks</hi> of <hi>Cains-Generation,</hi> and <hi>Balaams,</hi> who are of old ordained for <hi>Condemnation,</hi> which <hi>condemnation</hi> is the <hi>Light,</hi> which to it in all your Conſciences I do ſpeak, which is your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, who, to it, contrary do walk; and you that hold up ſuch as receives gifts and rewards, you hold <hi>Balaam,</hi> and follow <hi>Balaam,</hi> and ſo turn from the true <hi>Prophets</hi> of the Lord, which ever teſtified againſt ſuch; and you that do maintain ſuch, maintaine <hi>Balaam,</hi> and are blind, witneſſed againſt with the Scriptures; let that in your Conſcience, and the Scriptures judge you, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it do act, and that which gave forth the Scriptures, who holds up <hi>Balaam,</hi> and ſuch as goes in his way; you love not God that doth ſee; but love the world, and are of the world, and the world loves their own, ſuch as goes in <hi>Balaams</hi> way, receives gifts &amp; rewards, the wages of unrighteouſneſs, and in <hi>Cains</hi> way, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes; the world loves, yea, and fights for with ſtones, ſtaves, and their Books; and they have a Popiſh Law to guard them, which guarded the Papiſts; and ſuch as go in <hi>Cains</hi> way, and <hi>Balaams</hi> way, are not Gods, but the worlds, and the world loves them, as you may read, in <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude,</hi> Let the Apoſtles words there judg you, and you that holds up ſuch as bears rule by their means, ye are not of God, and ye hold up ſuch as are not of God, but of the world, and the world loves her own; and the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied againſt ſuch, who was of God, as you may read, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5. and ſuch Shepheards as ſeek for their gain from their Quarter, are the worlds, and the world loves her own<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for ſuch are not of God, for the Lord ſent his Prophet to cry againſt ſuch; as you may read, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. and ſuch are the worlds, and not Gods, as ſeek for the fleece; ſuch Shepheards as makes a prey upon the people, and devours them, ſuch are the worlds, and the world loves her own and the Lord ſent his Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to cry out againſt ſuch; as you may read, <hi>Ezek. 34. And ſuch are not of God, but of the world, and ſuch the world fights for, with Clubs, States, and Stones:</hi> And ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118787:3"/>
as are <hi>Hirelings,</hi> which the Lord ſent <hi>Ieremiah</hi> and <hi>Micah</hi>-to cry againſt, theſe are the <hi>Worlds Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> &amp; not the <hi>Lords,</hi> and theſe are their <hi>Fruits</hi> and <hi>Mark,</hi> and the world hears their own, and loves ſuch, and fights for ſuch, and perſecutes the dear <hi>Children</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> which are moved to cry out againſt them, and ſuch <hi>Magistrates</hi> as be ignorant of the true and wiſe <hi>God,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes them, to the fulfilling of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and ſuch as are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of men <hi>Master,</hi> ſtands praying in the <hi>Synagogues,</hi> the chiefeſt Seats in the <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> cryed wo againſt, are the <hi>worlds,</hi> not <hi>Chriſts,</hi> and the <hi>world</hi> loves her own, and fights for ſuch as are called of men <hi>Maſter,</hi> ſtands praying in the <hi>Synagogues,</hi> and have the chiefeſt Seats in the <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> the <hi>world</hi> hears ſuch, and not <hi>Chriſt;</hi> they that are of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hears not ſuch, but <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the Son of <hi>God;</hi> and all ſuch as are called of men <hi>maſter,</hi> goes in <hi>Cains</hi> way, and <hi>Balaams</hi> way, are the worlds, which receives the <hi>wages</hi> of <hi>unrighteouſneſs Gifts</hi> and <hi>rewards,</hi> and are <hi>perſecutors,</hi> and the <hi>worlds,</hi> and held up by the world, and the <hi>world</hi> loves ſuch and fights for ſuch, and ſuch their <hi>perſons</hi> muſt be reſpected, and ſuch regards not the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but caſts it behind their backs, and ſuch as theſe are their <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>marks,</hi> and they that do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect <hi>perſons,</hi> are convinced by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to be tranſgreſſors, &amp; he that breaks one point breaks, all &amp; they that cannot reſpect <hi>perſons,</hi> but the Law of <hi>God,</hi> with the world perſecuted and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, witneſs the <hi>Goales</hi> now in the <hi>Nation</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> To the <hi>Light</hi> in all your <hi>Conſciences</hi> I ſpeak which comes from <hi>Ieſus,</hi> which lets you ſee the <hi>world,</hi> and lets you ſee all that which they that dwelt in the Light were ſent to teſtifie againſt, and lets you ſee the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which is one with that of <hi>God</hi> in every mans <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which if you love this <hi>Light,</hi> it wil let you ſee <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> from whence it comes, and wil let you ſee all the <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>marks</hi> of the worlds teachers, which if you hate the Light, and act thoſe things contrary to the Light, as they who in the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> declared againſt the <hi>Prophets, Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> with the <hi>Light</hi> you are all ſeen, and your actions contrary to the <hi>Light,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118787:3"/>
with the <hi>Light</hi> you are condemned, for this is the condemnation the <hi>Light</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and to you this is the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you are all warned in your life time; all ſuch <hi>teachers</hi> as bear rule by their means, are the <hi>worlds,</hi> which the <hi>Lord</hi> ſent <hi>Ieremiah</hi> to cry againſt ſuch, and the <hi>world</hi> fights for ſuch, and ſay they are <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſuch as are called <hi>Miniſters,</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and perſecutes, to hold up their <hi>kingdome,</hi> that their folly may be made manifeſt, and their fruits and marks may be ſeen, and all ſuch ſhepheards that ſeeks for their <hi>gain</hi> from their <hi>quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> that the <hi>Lord</hi> ſent I <hi>ſay</hi> to cry againſt, and all ſuch ſhepheards as ſeek for the <hi>fleece,</hi> and make a <hi>prey</hi> upon the people, which the Lord ſent <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to cry againſt; are the worlds, and the world loves ſuch, and fights for ſuch ſhepheards, let their daily practiſe judge, and all ſuch as are Hirelings, and preach peace to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but if they put not into their mouthes, they prepare war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; theſe are of the <hi>world,</hi> and the <hi>world</hi> loves ſuch, and fights for ſuch, let their practiſe judg, all ſuch as are called of men Maſters, ſtands praying in the Synagogues, and have the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Seats in the Aſſemblies, are the worlds, for <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wo againſt ſuch, and all ſuch as goes in <hi>Cains</hi> waie, and <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> waie, and ſpeaks a <hi>divination</hi> of their own <hi>brain,</hi> are the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie dreamers, and through Covetouſneſs makes merchandiſe of the people through feigned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> words; theſe are all the worlds, and theſe are their Fruits and Marks, contrary to the Prophets, Apoſtles and Chriſt, with the Light was they all teſtifyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and it is witneſſed and ſeen now in this Nation, that the World holds up ſuch, and Love<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Fights for ſuch contrary to the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles, Let their practiſe and the Scriptures be their Iudge, and that in their Conſciences their Condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118787:4"/>Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Beware of ſalſe Prophets, which come to you in Sheeps Cloathing, but inwardly are raving Wolves;</hi> now here are ſome Marks and Fruits by which they ſhould know the falſe Prophets they are inwardly raving Wolves, they are as the bryers and the thorns, and corrupt trees, that bring forth the evil Fruit, their houſe is upon the ſand; and it is not every one that ſaith Lord, Lord, that enters into the Kingdome of God, but he that doth the wil of the Lord: And here the falſe Prophets gets the Sheeps Cloathing, that which cloathed the Sheep, and ſo the good words deceives the ſimple, but they themſelves are as thorns and bryars, and inwardly ravening wolves; and theſe are the Marks and Fruits of the falſe Prophets, though outwardly they appear beautiful, as yon may read, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. And ſecondly, more Marks and Fruits you may ſee of the falſe Prophets, they be they which are out of Chriſts Doctrine, love the chiefeſt place at Feaſts, the chiefeſt ſeats in the <hi>Aſsemblies,</hi> greetings in the <hi>Markets,</hi> and to be called of men <hi>Maſter,</hi> which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Be ye not called of men Maſter, ye have one Maſter,</hi> to wit, <hi>Christ, and ye are all Brethren: &amp; he that will be greatest among you, let him be your ſervant:</hi> And here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain they be out of <hi>Christs Doctrine,</hi> and by their <hi>Fruits</hi> you may know them. Read <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. throughout, it is worth your reading and obſerving, for to diſcover to you the <hi>Fruits</hi> and <hi>Marks</hi> of the falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> or <hi>Phariſees<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which Chriſt cryed wo againſt: And again you may read <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. the <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Fruits</hi> of the falſe <hi>Prophets</hi> and the <hi>Antichriſts</hi> ſuch as are drawing people to lo here, and lo there, whenas Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Go not forth,</hi> who lighteth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that commeth into the world. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 9. that with this Light they may come to ſee him, and all the <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Fruits</hi> of the falſe Prophets. And again you may ſee in <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. ſuch as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſent forth, they was not to take <hi>Gold</hi> nor <hi>Silver,</hi> nor <hi>Money,</hi> nor two Coats, nor a ſtaffe, he told them they ſhould be ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Synagogues; and here you may ſee ſuch ſcourge in their Synagogues, which takes the <hi>Gold</hi> the <hi>Silver,</hi> the <hi>Money,</hi> the <hi>ſtaff,</hi> and ſuch other things as are mentioned in the ſame <hi>Chapter,</hi> contrarie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118787:4"/>
to Chriſts command: and here you may ſee the Marks and fruits of the falſe Teachers: and again, they are ſuch that ſware, which Chriſt Ieſus ſaith, <hi>Sweare not at all,</hi> and ſo there they do not own his Doctrine, but are againſt it, and are Antichriſts, and by their Marks and Fruits they are known. And again they are ſuch as ſerve not our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chrict,</hi> but their own bellies, and through flattering ſpeeches deceives the ſimple, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. And they are ſuch as ſues men at the Law, and here they are out of Chriſts <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and by their Fruit we know them, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6. and ſuch are they as transform themſelves as Miniſters of righteouſneſs, and as an <hi>Angell</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> but by their Marks and Fruits we know them, and they are ſuch as confeſs they have not the ſame Spirit that gave forth the Scriptures, and ſo draws people from the Spirit, and ſo bewitch them <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. and are ſuch as have the form of godlineſs, but the power deny, which are to be turned awaie from, they are headdie, high minded, boaſters, and proud, unholie, curſed ſpeakers, truce-breakers, falſe-accuſers, intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, fierce, no lovers at all of thoſe that are good, lovers of pleaſure more than lovers of God: Of this ſort are they which creep into Houſes, leading ſillie women captive, which be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of the truth, but doth reſiſt the truth, as <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres,</hi> did, being men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the Faith of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which reſpect no mans perſon, which purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the; Heart Here by their Marks and Fruits you ſhal know the falſe Teachers, the falſe Prophets, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and they are ſuch as are puffed up, knowing nothing, doting about Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſtrife of words, whereof commeth Envy, ſtrife, railings and Evil ſurmizings, froward diſputations, men of corrupt minds deſtitute of the truth, which think gain is godlineſs; from ſuch ſeperate thy ſelf: Here is their Marks and Fruits by which thou maiſt know them. 1 <hi>Tim. 6. And they are ſuch as deſire after Money, and luſteth after it, which draws men into perdition, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and noyſome Luſts, and ſo are erred from the Faith.</hi> And
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118787:5"/>
ther <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Fruits,</hi> Oh man of God, flee theſe things and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after righteouſneſs, and godlineſs, faith, love, patience, and meekneſs, and lay hold on eternall life; and prophane <hi>bablings, ungodlineſs,</hi> put away fooliſh and unlearned Queſtions, which genders ſtrife, and their words ſhall fret as a Canker; and here is their <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Fruits, 2 Tim.</hi> 2. and are ſuch as are given to tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Fables,</hi> and <hi>Stories,</hi> having itching <hi>ears,</hi> and ſo are turned from the Doctrine of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. whenas the Lord ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not walk about with Tales among any people: Levit.</hi> 19. and in <hi>Titus</hi> you may ſee the <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Fruits</hi> of the falſe Teachers, they are <hi>Vain-talkers, Deceivers</hi> of minds, not holding faſt the faithfull word, according to Doctrine, which teacheth for filthy lucre ſake, whoſe mouthes muſt be ſtopped, evil beaſts and ſlow-bellies reprove them ſharply; here you may ſee more <hi>marks</hi> and <hi>fruits</hi> of the falſe Prophets.</p>
            <p>Again you may prove them by the Apoſtles Rule, he muſt not be ſlandered of Riot, not taking heed to <hi>Fables,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of men that turn away from the Truth, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>And again he muſt be one that is temperate, and modeſt, and harmleſs, apt to teach, unreproveable, the Huſband of one Wife; and not given to joyne, no ſtriker, not given to filthy Lucre, one that can rule his own houſe honeſtly, if he cannot, how can hee take care for the Church of God? He muſt be grave, not double tongued; and firſt, let them be proved, and then let them mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter if they be found blameleſs, and here is the Marks and Fruits of a falſe Teacher, and how a true Teacher may be known from a falſe, and you that take any without proofes, are not them that proves all things, and holds faſt that which is good, as you may read, 1 <hi>Tim. 3. 1 Theſs.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118787:5"/>Again, the falſe Prophets are ſuch as makes merchandiſe of the word, through ſeigned words and covetouſueſs, and ſpeaks great ſwelling words through the luſts of the fleſh, promiſing liberty, are themſelves ſervants of corruptions, for of whom a man is overcome he is in bondage, and here is Marks and Fruits of the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and they are ſuch as ſport themſelves in the day time, with wantonneſs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orgh the luſts of the fleſh, live delitiouſly, delighting themſelves, and feaſting with you (in their deceivings,) hearts exerciſed with covetouſneſs, beguiling the ſouls that are not eſtabliſhed, as natural bruit beaſts to be deſtroyed, periſh in their own corruptions, by reaſon of whom, the way of truth is evil ſpoken of; and many follow their pernicious wayes: Here is the <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Fruits</hi> of the falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> and ſuch as deny the Lord Jeſus that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; there is the end of the falſe <hi>Prophets, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. And they are ſuch as are giving private interpretations of the Scriptures, which came not by the wil of man, neither is it of any private interpretation; and here is another Mark which comes from the private interpretations, which fils the world ſo ful of opinions; ſo as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>every Spirit is not to be believed, but they are to be tryed;</hi> that ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Jeſus is come in the fleſh, is not of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but is Antichriſt, of whom ye have heard ſhould come; but now already is come into the world; look to your ſelves, whoſoever tranſgreſſeth and abideth not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God, he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth in the Doctrine of Chriſt, he hath both the father and the ſon; and if there come any among you and bring not this Doctrine, receive him not into your houſes, norbid him <hi>God ſpeed,</hi> leſt ye be partakers of his evil deeds, as you may read in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of <hi>Iohn, and he that hath the form of godlineſs and not the power, from ſuch turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way:</hi> And here you may ſee more of the Marks and Fruits of the falſe Prophets and Deceivers, and they are ſuch as turn the grace of God into wantonneſs, denying God the only Lord, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, though they have the form of godlineſs, but denyes the power; and as raging waves of the Sea, murmurers and complainers, walking after their own luſts, whoſe mouths ſpeak proud things, having mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage, following the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and of <hi>Balaams</hi> wages who periſhed in the gainſaying of <hi>Core;</hi> and mockers, which ſhould come in the laſt times, which ſhould walk after their ungodly luſts, having not the ſpirit, but having mens perſons in admiration, which is out of the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: And<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> here is more of the marks and fruits of the falſe Teachers, as you may read in Iude &amp; <hi>Iames</hi> 2, and are in the wiſdome which is below, where is envy and ſtrife, ſedition, and all manner of evil works, and here is the fruits of their wiſdome; ſo the wiſe man which is endued with knowledge, and the wiſdome of the Lord Jeſus the true Prophet ſees and ſavours the fruits and marks of the falſe Prophets, and ſuper fluity, and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and maliciouſneſs; theſe are the Fruits of them that deceives their own ſouls, that are ſpeakers of the Scriptures, and doth not live in the life, <hi>Iames 1: &amp; Iſay</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the fruits of the falſe Shepheards, and the marks, he ſaid they ſeeke for their gain from their quarter, and they was greedy Dogs, and many other Marks he gives them; and the Apoſtle bids Mark them that walk not according to the Doctrine of Chriſt. And <hi>Iſajah</hi> ſaith they are greedy and can never have enough; and here is the Marks and Fruits of the falſe Shepheards, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. ſhews how they may be known: And
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118787:6"/>
Again <hi>Ieremiah</hi> doth ſhew the Marks of the Falſe Prophets, how they ſpeak a viſion of their own heart, and not from the mouth of the Lord, and how they do not ſtand in the Lords counſel, but they are ſuch as uſed their tongues but the Lord ſent them not; and ſuch as run; but the Lord hath not ſpoken to them, and ſuch as by their lyes and their lightneſs, counſel the people to erre, and ſuch ſteals the word from their Neighbor.</p>
            <p>And againſt ſuch Prophets wil the Lord come, and the Lord tels ſuch his word is as a hammer, and as a fire; and here ye may ſee the Fruits and the Marks of the falſe Prophets, which gets the Letter, and tels people it is the word, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And again <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſhews the Marks and Fruits, and the horrible filthy thing, the Prophets propheſie lies, and the Prieſts bear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ule by their means, and the people love to have it ſo: O fooliſh people, eyes, and do not ſee, ears, and do not hear! fear ye not me ſaith the Lord? <hi>Ier. 5. &amp; Ezek.</hi> 34. you may read how he ſets forth the Marks and Fruits of the falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> how they make a <hi>prey</hi> vpon the <hi>People,</hi> and devour them; And again <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 3. how he doth ſhew forth the <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Fruits</hi> of the <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> and he ſaith they deceive the people, <hi>They cry peace to them, but if a man do not put into their mouths, they prepare war aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſt him:</hi> here is one of their <hi>Marks,</hi> and he faith, <hi>they ſhall cover their lips, for they have no anſwer from</hi> God; therefore they tell people the <hi>Letter</hi> is the <hi>VVord,</hi> where it ſaith, <hi>God is the word. Iohn</hi> 1: And again <hi>Micah</hi> ſaith, <hi>They propheſie for Money, and teach for hire,</hi> and againſt ſuch was <hi>Micah</hi> ſent to cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and their <hi>Fruits,</hi> and by their <hi>Fruits</hi> and <hi>Marks</hi> they are known. And <hi>Mallachy</hi> he ſhews the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts</hi> and <hi>Marks</hi> of the Prieſts, <hi>VVhoſe bleſſings are curſed, whoſe ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d is corrupted, ſuch as neglect</hi> Gods <hi>command, Mall.</hi> 1. The <hi>Fruits</hi> of the Idol-Shepheards, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and the judgments of God that ſhall come upon them: and the Fruits of the falſe Faſt of hypocrites, which <hi>Zacharias</hi> was ſent to ſpeak againſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 7. there you may read, and how the Lord ſent <hi>Habuckuk</hi> to cry againſt the perſecutors, <hi>Hab. 1. &amp; Hoſ.</hi> 6. he ſets forth the fruits of the murtherous Prieſts, how they (as Thieves) wait for a man, ſo a company Prieſts murther in the way by conſent, for they work miſchief. And ye may read the Marks and Fruits of the falſe prophets in <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k.</hi> 13. and how they polluted the people for hand-fuls of Barly, and pieces of Bread, to ſlay the ſouls of them that ſhould not dye; and theſe are the fooliſh prophets that follow their own Spirits, and ſee nothing, and they ſay the Lord ſaith it, but the Lord hath not ſent them, and they made others to hope that they ſhould confirm to the words of the propheſie, theſe were them that daubed with untempred morter, and theſe are them that hunt ſouls, and theſe are like Foxes in the vaſt places, and theſe are them that have their pillows, and ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked; and here are the Marks and Fruits of the falſe prophets, which the Lord is againſt, which have their pillows under their arm, and wil not let their ſouls go; and here is he Mark &amp; the Fruit of the falſe prophets, and you may ſee the Fruits of the falſe prophets, which do diſcover the iniquity, in <hi>Lamen.</hi> 2. and <hi>Ier.</hi> 29. there ſhews the Marks and Fruits of the falſe prophets, how they propheſied lies in the name of the Lord God, and I have not ſent them ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>This is to all you that ſpeaks in his name, &amp; he hath not ſent you, here is a mark and a Fruit, by which ye may be known, and <hi>Ier.</hi> 14. there he ſhews the Marks and fruits of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118787:6"/>
the falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> how they ſpoke in his <hi>Name,</hi> and he hath not ſent them, neither command them, <hi>Neither ſpake</hi> I <hi>unto them, but they propheſie unto you a falſe viſion, and deceipt of their own heart,</hi> and propheſie in his name, and the Lord hath not ſent them; and here is Fruits and Marks how they may be known, which who was in the light diſcovered.</p>
            <p>And again you may ſee the Marks and fruits of the evil Paſtures, in the 10. of <hi>Ieremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> and their Marks and Fruits there, how they become as Beaſts, and have not ſought the Lord; and ye may ſee the Marks and Fruits of the chief Prieſts, which were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the unchangeable Prieſt; the chiefe Prieſts could tell <hi>Herod</hi> by the Scriptures, where Chriſt ſhould be born, when he gathered them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the chief Prieſts adjured Chriſt to tel them whether he was the Son of God, (though the chiefe Prieſts could tel by the Scriptures where he ſhould be born) yet they knew him not when he was come, for he was not born by the will of man: And then when Jeſus confeſſed he was the Son of God, the High Prieſts rent his cloathes, and ſaid he had ſpoken blaſphemy; ſo when the morning was come, all the Chiefe Prieſts and Elders took Counſel againſt Jeſus to put him to death, and led him away bound; and here was their Fruits, and is the Marks of the Chief Prieſts now: and <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> before whom he witneſſed a good Confeſſion; and the chiefe Prieſts and Elders, and all the Counſell, ſought falſe witneſſes againſt Jeſus to put him to death, and the High Prieſt mocked him, with the Scribes, and Elders, and Phariſes; and the chief Prieſts and Elders had perſw aded the people that they ſhould ask <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and deſtroy Jeſus; and here is their fruits and marks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And <hi>Iudas</hi> which betrayed Chriſt, had money of the Chief Prieſts, and came with a great multitude, with Swords and Staves from the High Prieſts to take Ieſus, and ſo when <hi>Iudas</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from Chriſt, he turned to the Prieſts, who was the betrayer to the murtherers, and when it was heard that Ieſus was riſen, and ſhewed to the high Prieſts, they gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together with the Elders, and took counſell, and gave large Money to the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, ſaying, ſay ye his Diſciples came by night, and ſtole him away whileſt we ſlept: and here is the Marks and Fruits of the prieſts and lyars, as you may read in <hi>Matthew,</hi> and ye may ſee the Marks and Fruits of the <hi>Chiefe priests</hi> who examined <hi>Stephen</hi> in the 7. of the <hi>Acts, Stephen</hi> for witneſſing forth <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the unchangeable Prieſt, was Stoned to Death, denying the Types: And <hi>Saul,</hi> whileſt he was under the Prieſts, had a Commiſſion from them to perſecute them which witneſſed the ſecond Prieſt-hood: and here was the Marks and Fruits of the firſt prieſt-hood, and of <hi>Saul</hi> while he was under it; and after <hi>Paul</hi> was perſecuted with the Chief Prieſts, and the Jews, when he was come to witneſs Chriſt Jeſus the ſecond prieſt-hood, and denie the Temple and the firſt prieſt-hod, <hi>Acts 24. &amp; Acts 17. &amp; Acts 21. &amp; Acts</hi> 22. 5. and many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Marks, and Fruits, you may read in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> how <hi>Iohn</hi> (by the ſpirit of the Lord) ſets them forth there, and in <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iude</hi> alſo.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118787:7"/>
               <p>THe word of the Lord God to all you which are called the two Mothers in this Nation, with them which do come from you, whom you have made Miniſters (as you call them,) they have told us Chriſt Jeſus hath ſent them, and we ſee now with the Light which comes from Jeſus Chriſt, that they are made Miniſters by the wil of man, and Chriſt Jeſus ſent them not, but their Mothers (as they call them) and they told us the Letter it was the Light, when the Letter ſaith, Chriſt is the Light; here we do charge them, both they and their Mothers, to be lyars, and to be adulterate from the Light, and knows nothing but the outſide, ſo with the Light they all lyars are to be condemned for the Lake, as its written, the lyars muſt have their portion in the Lake that burns, and they and their Mothers have filled this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ful of their lyes, but with the Light which comes from Jeſus Chriſt which never changes, they are comprehended with it, and condemned to the Lake of Lyars, and they told us the Sons and Children that came from their Mothers; that the Bible it was the Word, and the Bible ſaith, that <hi>in the beginning was the word and the word was God:</hi> And here again with the Light which comes from this word, which word endures for ever, which was before paper and ink was, and the Scriptures was given forth; and here again we do charge both the Mothers and their Sons to be lyars, and no Miniſters of the word, for they which was Miniſters of the word, and eye witneſſes, took in hand to ſet forth a Declaration in order, ſo it is a Declaration which the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word ſet forth, which word was in the beginning, by which all things was made and upheld by the word and power, the word became fleſh and dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and here thou that haſt ſit as Queen, and ſeen no ſorrow, and had many children, thy deſolation is comming and come, and the loſs of thy children, thy skirts are ſeen, and thy nakedneſs appears, and thy lewdneſs, and whoredomes, and witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, and lyes doth appear to all the children of the Light, who are in the Light that comprehends all the world, and reaches over it: And the Children which are come from their mothers, taught us and told us that <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latine,</hi> was the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall, and is the Originall, and ſuch learned men muſt open the Scriptures: and with the Light which is eternall, which is come from the Son of God, with it we do ſee that before <hi>Babell</hi> was, all the earth was of one Language, and then <hi>Nimrod</hi> the cunning hunter before the Lord, which came out of <hi>Ham's</hi> Stock, the Father of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> who was curſed, he was the beginner of the building of <hi>Babell,</hi> whom God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded into many Languages, and we do ſee that <hi>Pilate</hi> which crucified Chriſt had this Originall, <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> and ſet it over Chriſt; ſo here with the <hi>light</hi> we ſee them <hi>Babylon</hi> building up, and throwing down, with their many Languages which is confuſion, and their <hi>Mother</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of Harlots, which teacheth them many languages, which is trimmed and deceives the Nations, but with the Light which commeth from Jeſus Chriſt, ſhe and her Sons are comprehended, and they can go no further then Babel, which are Babylon, for with the Light you are ſeen, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and judged, with the word which was before any language was, by which all things was made, as is ſaid before, and here you are hammered, who are in many languages, with the word which was as a hammer to beat you in pieces, and with the word you are to be cut and divided aſſunder, for the word is as a two-edged ſword, &amp; the word is as a fire to burn you up, who be in the many Languages; and to you all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118787:7"/>
is the word of the Lord, which doth endure for ever, and who are redeemed, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed forth of the many languages, and is come before Babel was: And the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which come from their Mother, told us that ſprinkling Infants was the Baptiſm, and the Steeplehouſe was the <hi>Church,</hi> of a Sacrament, which there is no ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and ſo here again with the Light which Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightned us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, we ſee they taught us more lyes, and ſo with the Light they are to be condemned, as I ſaid unto you before, for the light that gave forth the Scriptures ſaith, the Church is in God, and with the Spirit they was all baptiſed into one body, and was made all to drink in one ſpirit; with the Light we do ſee and witneſs this, praiſed be God, which hath ſeperated us from this lying Generation, which holds up theſe Mothers and their Sons, which be Teachers of Lyes. And they did tel us theſe Children that comes from their Mothers, that they were the miniſters of God, and his Prophets, and his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; now with the Light which comes from Chriſt Jeſus we do them all ſee to be ſuch as be out of the truth, and ſuch as the Lord ſent <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cah</hi> to cry againſt, that are hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, they that doth not put into their mouths they prepare war againſt them, they that doth, to them they preach peace, and boaſt, and ſay, is not the Lord amongſt them? none evil can come to them; who ſee the evil and tranſgreſſion, with the light which comes from Chriſt comprehended they are, with the Light the Prophet that ſaw Chriſt, witneſſed againſt ſuch with the ſame Light, which Light we witneſs made manifeſt, which never changes, with which light all deceits and deceivers are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and with the Light we do ſee them that come from their mothers, to be ſuch as ſeeks for their gain from their quarter, as beareth rule by their means, as ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for the fleece, which the Lord ſent his Prophets to cry againſt, which was in the Light, vvhich vvith the Light they ſavv Chriſt, vvhich Chriſt hath enlightned us with, with which Light we ſee the ſame as the <hi>Prophets</hi> did, which was witneſſes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the <hi>Light,</hi> and ſo here we do ſee them to be deceivers that goes into the world, who uſeth their tongues, and ſaith the Lord ſaith, when he never ſpoke to them, and ſpeaks a divination of their own brain, and follow their own Spirits, which are the dreamers, with the <hi>Light</hi> they are ſeen which never changes, and with it which is eternall all comprehended; and to you this is the eternal word of God, and theſe Sons that come from their <hi>Mothers,</hi> told us they was Chriſts Embaſſador; with the <hi>Light</hi> which comes from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath <hi>enlightned</hi> us withall, we do ſee them to be holding up the figures in the firſt Covenant, and their <hi>Mothers</hi> to be lyars, and they no Embaſſadors of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which takes <hi>tythes</hi> of the people, and if they will not give it them who witneſſes the <hi>unchangeable P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ieſt, Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and deny the <hi>chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable,</hi> they ſue them at the Law, and cauſe them to be hailed before magiſtrates, <hi>Courts, &amp; Seſſions,</hi> &amp; put them in priſons, becauſe they wil not pay them <hi>tythes,</hi> here you are declared to the whole <hi>nation</hi> to be lyars, and no <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for whom he ſent forth, he ſent forth freely and denyed all oppreſſion; here with the Scripture it ſelf you are judged to be out of the practiſe of them that he ſent forth, &amp; you that take <hi>tythes</hi> of the people, &amp; brings the Scripture for your <hi>rule,</hi> as they that received <hi>tythes</hi> in old time, which had a <hi>ſtore-houſe</hi> to put it in, &amp; them that did not bring their <hi>tythes</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il it, they robbed <hi>God,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Mallachie,</hi> and the Prieſts which received the <hi>tythes,</hi> the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118787:8"/>
ſtrangers; the fatherleſs, &amp; the widdows was to come within the Prieſts Gate, &amp; he was to miniſter forth to the ſtranger, the widdows, &amp; the fatherleſs, that there might be no beggar in Iſrael; now to you that receives <hi>tythes</hi> I ſpeak, who are neither miniſters of the Goſpel, nor miniſters of the firſt covenant, but jugglers, as you call it, are made manifeſt to all that be in the light.</p>
               <p>Now it you ſay, give <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, which are <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and bring that for your Cloak for to hold up the figure, the firſt <hi>prieſt-hood,</hi> that Cloak wil not you cover, but your <hi>nakedneſs</hi> and <hi>whoredome</hi> from the <hi>Light</hi> is ſeen, and with the <hi>Light</hi> are all to be <hi>condemned,</hi> from the <hi>Firſt Covenant,</hi> and the <hi>Second</hi> both, who are found in the <hi>truth</hi> in neither, for the firſt <hi>prieſt-hood</hi> who had the <hi>Store-houſe,</hi> into which the <hi>Tythes</hi> was received, which the <hi>priests</hi> miniſtred forth to the <hi>strangers, widdows,</hi> and <hi>Fatherleſs,</hi> a Figure of the <hi>unchangeable Prieſt, Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> who miniſters out of the everlaſting <hi>Treaſure,</hi> and while the firſt <hi>prieſt-hood</hi> was ſtanding, <hi>Store-houſes</hi> and <hi>Tythes</hi> was <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched</hi> up, it was before <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> was preached up, the <hi>unchangeable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rieſt,</hi> over the <hi>houſhould</hi> of God, then the unchangeable was confeſſed with them, and the changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>prieſt-hood, ſtore-houſe,</hi> and <hi>Tythes</hi> was denyed, diſanulled, and of no effect, which the deceivers of the world for their own ends, Mothers and Sons brings up tythes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſay they are Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but with the <hi>Light</hi> which comes from <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> we do ſee who they are, and what they are, that have told us theſe lyes, ſo with the Light they are to be condemned, and their Mothers and their Children, and their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lites that they have begotten: To the Light in all your Conſciences I ſpeak, which ſhall witneſs me eternally, and you all condemn that hate it, and hold up ſuch things; and to you this is the word of God, that you might ſee your ſelves what you are: and they have told us which came from their Mothers, that they was in Chriſt ſteed, and he ſent them; but with the eternal Light which never changes, which Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightned us withall, we do them ſee in the ſteps of the Scribes and Phariſees, garniſhing the Sepulchers of the Righteous, building the Tombs of the Prophets and Apoſtles, as whited walls, outſide Sepulchers, and Graves which buries the juſt, whoſe hands are ful of Blood, Envie, and Hatred, which be ſuch as are called of men Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and have the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies, ſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th praying in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, in the ſteps of the phraiſees their Fathers, which were enemies to Chriſt, as you may read, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. And with the Light which comes from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, you are all ſeen, and with it to be condemned, no cloak can cover you, but you are ſeen with all the Children of Light, praiſed be the Lord God.</p>
               <p>And the word of the Lord God to all you who ſaith that you are gifted men, who ſaith that you are not made Miniſters by theſe two Mothers, but you are experienced men, and received a gift, and you muſt exerciſe your gift, and you wil have 40. 50. 60. 80. pounds a year, more or leſs, as you can get it for your gift: You I do charge, in the preſence of the living God, to be ſuch as erred from the Spirit, as your Father Balaam did, are turned from the commands of God, as <hi>Cain</hi> did, and you are in the ſelfe-ſeperation, whoſe fruit ſhall wither; you are the Clouds without water, the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſtars, who receive the wages of unrighteouſneſs, who ſpeaks high ſwelling words, through the luſts of the fleſh, which hath mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage; you are the wells without water, which ſay you are experienced men,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118787:8"/>
and gifted men, and go ſell your gift to the world; here again I do charge you, in the preſence of the living God, to be lyars, diſſemblers, and deceivers of the world, and contrary to the Scriptures, and never exerciſed the gift of God, for the Elect you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deceive which have received the gift of God, which is perfect, which cannot be bought and ſold for money, ſo your gifts which can be ſold for money are not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from God, but the Light which comes from Chriſt Jeſus which is eternall, you and your gifts are to be condemned, which can be bought and ſold for money, you are them that ſeperate your ſelves, not having the Spirit, with the Light you are ſeen and your fruit which withers, and with it which never changeth you and it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; to that in your Conſciences which never changes I ſpeak, which ſhall wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs me, which condemns you: to you this is the eternall word of God. And you that ſay you are Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and declare againſt theſe two <hi>Mothers</hi> before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and her <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> and you your ſelves are ſuch as are called of men <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> have the <hi>chiefeſt place</hi> in the <hi>aſſemblies,</hi> and ſtand praying in the <hi>Synagogues,</hi> which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt cryed wo againſt, and now ſay the <hi>Scriptures</hi> is your rule, here with Chriſts words are you judged, and ſeen to be deceivers that deceives the world; but they who are in <hi>Christ,</hi> which cryed wo againſt ſuch as you and the <hi>Scribes,</hi> you cannot deceive. And you <hi>Teachers</hi> that ſay the Scripture is your rule, and are ſeperate from theſe two Mothers and her Children, before mentioned, and which ſay you muſt obſerve the commands of Chriſt as ordinances, and are zealous of the outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, as the <hi>Iews</hi> was, and yet ye do not believe that Jeſus Chriſt doth enlighten every one that comes into the world; here you and your zeal are to be candemned, for it is without the knowledg of God; to it I bear record eternally, and the commands of Chriſt you know not, and with the Light which comes from Chriſt Jeſus, you and your zeal is to be condemned, which is taken on from the Letter, in that mind and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which acteth contrary to the Light, ſo you are in that ſtate of the Scribes, whoſe mouth muſt be ſtopped.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
